A Catalog of Instrumental Music Published Before ca. 1800 in the Alexander Mackay-Smith Collection of the University of Virginia
University of Virginia Library
Mackay-Smith Collection, University of Virginia
Alexander Mackay-Smith Collection
1689-1827
University of Virginia. Small Special Collections Library Small Special Collections Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
265 items
The Mackay-Smith Collection's greatest strength is in contemporary editions of 18th-century instrumental music, particularly trio sonatas. The collection shows similarity to the music section of Jefferson's catalogue of 1783. The trio sonatas of Carlo Antonio Campioni (1720-1788), one of Jefferson's favorite composers, are especially well represented.
Alexander Mackay-Smith
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
Introduction
"The collection was not brought together by writing big checks to leading dealers. On the contrary it represents days and weeks spent in the bookstalls and shops of London, Paris and Berlin, thumbing over dust-laden stacks of music and piles of books. It represents many hours of study, many hundreds of letters. It was never the sort of collection gathered just for exhibition purposes, but a working library..."1
Alexander Mackay-Smith's "working library" today forms the nucleus of the University of Virginia's Music Library. The Mackay-Smith Collection, presented to the University in 1946, includes complete runs of what at that time constituted virtually all the major musicological journals, an impressive array of major reference works, bibliographies, printed library catalogues, monographs, and, above all, scores.
The collection's greatest strength is in contemporary editions of 18th-century instrumental music, particularly trio sonatas. An accomplished amateur violinist, Mackay-Smith acquired much of his chamber music for purely practical purposes. His chamber music partners included his brother, Carleton Sprague Smith, flutist and chief of the New York Public Library's Music Division from 1931 to 1943 and again from 1946 to 1959; Elizabeth Sprague Coolidge, pianist, composer, and patroness of music; and Constance Darden, violinist and violist, wife of the University of Virginia's President, Colgate Darden.
The majority of the works represented in this catalogue were purchased in Paris and London between 1928 and 1934. After graduating from Harvard in 1924, Mackay-Smith spent several years in Europe:
I bought my first early music from Harold Reeves in London in the summer of 1928 when I was able to acquire virtually all the 18th century editions, particularly of trio music, which he then had in stock, going back not only through his current but also through earlier catalogues, picking out numbers which remained unsold. It is almost a shame today to think of the prices at which such things were then available, one or two pounds apiece.2
Otto Haas, in Berlin and then later in London, was another source for much of the music described here. Following World War II, Mackay-Smith deposited his entire music collection with the University of Virginia Library:
The University seemed like a logical place to deposit [it], since my children are descended from Thomas Jefferson; since, as you well know, Jefferson played the violin almost every day of his life...3
It is particularly fitting, I think, that the chamber music for violin which Thomas Jefferson so enjoyed playing should now be fully represented at the University which he founded.4
The Mackay-Smith Collection in fact shows similarity to the music section of Jefferson's own catalogue of 1783. It is scarcely coincidental that the trio sonatas of Carlo Antonio Campioni (1720-1788), one of Jefferson's favorite composers, are especially well represented. Jefferson had at one point taken the trouble to transcribe some 38 incipits of works by Campioni already in his library, with a note in the margin to a London dealer asking for any other works he had also composed, "Solos, Duets, or Trios. Printed copies would be preferred..."5
It was in much the same systematic fashion that Alexander Mackay-Smith developed his own collection of instrumental chamber music, with special emphasis on the trio sonata. A lawyer by profession, Mackay-Smith might also confess, as had Jefferson, that "music is the favorite passion of my soul."6 Jefferson, however, had been forced to concede that "fortune has cast my lot in a country where it is in a state of deplorable barbarism." That these circumstances no longer obtain is due in no small measure to the efforts of Alexander Mackay-Smith and other collectors like him.
Editorial Method
The form of entry for each composer's name follows that in the Library of Congress authority file, where such an entry exists, or The New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians, 2nd ed.. In the case of composers whose works were first published during both the 18th and 19th centuries, only composers born before 1770 have been included. This is approximately the same criterion for inclusion in RISM Series A/I.
A brief filing title is provided to facilitate browsing and ensure a logical and consistent sequence among entries. The form is essentially that established by the second edition of the
Anglo-American Cataloguing Rules (Chicago: American Library Association, 1979 )
. A few minor exceptions have been adopted for the sake of both brevity and clarity.
Unless otherwise indicated, all individual parts within a set have identical title-pages. The format (folio, quarto, etc.) is based on the number of times the original sheets of paper have been folded to make individual leaves.7 The terminology for the oblong formats is that suggested by D. W. Krummel.8 Two sets of dimensions are given for all engraved title-pages: the first represents the imaginary rectangle that would enclose all elements of the engraved surface; the second measurement, in parentheses, represents the plate mark. The names of individual parts are transcribed exactly as they appear on the parts themselves, usually as running heads. The system used for describing pagination has been taken from Cecil Hopkinson's various bibliographies of Berlioz, Gluck, Puccini, etc., and is self-explanatory. No attemp has been made to collate gatherings.9
The title of each work and its sequence of movements and keys are transcribed as they appear on the first part listed in the work's contents. Any exceptions to this, the primary source of information, are specifically noted in square brackets.
For dates, the terminology used is that recommended by the
International Association of Music Libraries' Guide for Dating Early Published Music
.10 Whenever possible, dates of issue are provided; for lack of sufficient evidence, however, most dates in this catalogue must be considered dates of editions.
All citation to the Répertoire international des sources musicales, unless otherwise noted, are to
Series A/I, Einzeldrucke vor 1801, edited by Karl-Heinz Schlager (Kassel: Bärenreiter, 1971-1981)
. If the Mackay-Smith exemplar differs significantly from the entry appearing in RISM, discrepancies are noted in parentheses following the RISM number.
The dates that appear at the end of many of the call numbers derive from the original cataloguing of the collection at the University of Virginia in the late 1940s. Although an integral part of the call number, they have no significance in and of themselves.
Notes
1 Alexender Mackay-Smith to Stephen Tuttle, Professor of Music, 16 July 1948, Mackay-Smith papers, Alderman Library, University of Virginia.
2 Mackay-Smith to Jean Bonin, Music Librarian, 30 July 1974.
3 Ibid.
4 Mackay-Smith to Tuttle, 16 July 1948.
5 Both the music section of the 1783 catalogue and the Campioni incipits (undated) are reproduced and transcribed in Carolyn Galbraith Nolan's "Thomas Jefferson, Gentleman Musician" (M.A. thesis, University of Virginia, 1967). Nolan's transcriptions of the catalogue also appears in Helen Cripe's Thomas Jefferson and Music (Charlottesville: University Press of Virginia, 1974), pp. 97-104.
6 Thomas Jefferson to Giovanni Fabbroni, 8 June 1778, in
The Papers of Thomas Jefferson, edited by Julian Boyden, v. 2 (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1950 ), p. 196
.
7 See
Ronald B. McKerrow, An Introduction to Bibliography ( Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1927 ), pp. 164-174
.
8
D. W. Krummel, "Oblong Format in Early Music Books," The Library, 5th series, 26 ( 1971 ), pp. 312-324
.
9 As Krummel has pointed out, the leaves of most engraved music after 1700 are gathered either singly or in twos (
"Bibliography of Music," The New Grove, v. 2
, p. 683) "and the important changes in text usually took place on the plates, making the assembly largely irrelevant for textual work." (
"Musical Functions and Bibliographical Forms," The Library, 5th series, 31 [ 1976 ], p. 337
).
10
Compiled by D. W. Krummel (Hackensack, N.J.: Joseph Boonin, 1974 )
.
List of Works Cited in Abbreviated Form
Bauer, Carla Christine. Michael Blavets Flötenmusik. Freiburg: Hochschule-Verlag, 1981.
B. [Handel]
Bell, A. Craig. Handel: Chronological Thematic Catalogue. Darley: Grian-Aig Press, 1972.
B. [Pleyel]
Benton, Rita. Ignace Pleyel: A Thematic Catalogue of His Compositions. New York: Pendragon Press, 1977.
B. [Tartini]
Brainard, Paul. Le sonate per violino di Giuseppe Tartini: catalog tematico. Milan: Carisch, 1975.
BUCEM
The British Union-Catalogue of Early Music Before the Year 1801: A Record of the Holdings of over One Hundred Libraries Throughout the British Isles. 2 vols. Edited by Edith B. Schnapper. London: Butterworths, 1957.
CPM
The Catalogue of Printed Music in the British Library to 1980. Edited by Laureen Baillie. London: K. G. Saur, 1981-
Devriès, Anik. Édition et commerce de la musique graveée a Paris dans la première moitié du XVIIIe siècle: les Boivin, les Leclerc. Geneva: Minkoff, 1976.
Devriès-Lesure
Devriès, Anik, and François Lesure. Dictionnaire des éditeurs de musique français. Geneva: Minkoff, 1979-
D.
Dounias, Minos. Die Volinkonzerte Giuseppe Tartinis. Munich: Druck der Salesianischen Offizin, 1935.
Fred, Herbert William. "The Instrumental Music of Johann Christoph Pepusch." Ph.D. dissertation, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill, 1961.
G.
Gérard, Yves. Thematic, Bibliographical, and Critical Catalogue of the Works of Luigi Boccherini. London: Oxford University Press, 1969.
Haas, Otto. Catalogue No. 20: The Valuable Music Library formed by Alfred Moffat, Esq. London: Haas, [ 1944 ].
Hopkinson, Cecil. A Dictionary of Parisian Music Publishers, 1700-1950. New York: Da Capo, 1979 (reprint of the London, 1954, ed.).
Hob.
Hoboken, Anthony van. Joseph Haydn: Thematisch-bibliographisches Werkverzeichnis. 3 vols. Mainz: B. Schott's Söhne, 1957-78.
Humphries-Smith
Humphries, Charles, and William C. Smith. Music Publishing in the British Isles, from the Beginning until the Middle Part of the Nineteenth Century. 2nd ed. New York: Barnes & Noble, 1970.
J.
Jenkins, Newell, and Bathia Churgin. Thematic Catalogue of the Works of Giovanni Battista Sammartini: Orchestral and Vocal Music. Cambridge, Mass.: Published for the American Musicological Society by Harvard University Press, 1976.
Johansson/French
Johansson, Cari. French Music Publishers' Catalogues of the Second Half of the Eighteenth Century. 2 vols. Stockholm: Kungl. Musikaliska Akademiens bibliothek, 1955.
Johansson/Hummel
Johansson, Cari. J. J. & B. Hummel Music-Publishing and Thematic Catalogues. 3 vols. Stockholm: Almquist & Wiksell, 1972.
Knape, Walter. Bibliographisch-thematisches Verzeichnis der Kompositionen von Karl Friedrich Abel. Cuxhaven: W. Knape, 1972.
K.
Köchel, Ludwig, Ritter von. Chronologisch-thematisches Verzeichnis sämtlicher Tonwerke Wolfgang Amadé Mozarts. 6th ed., edited by Franz Giegling, Alexander Weinmann, and Gerd Sievers. Wiesbaden: Breitkopf & Härtel, 1964.
Lesure/Bibliographie
Lesure, François. Bibliographie des éditions musicales publiées par Estienne Roger et Michel-Charles Le Cène, Amsterdam, 1696-1743. Paris: Société française de musicologie, 1969.
Lesure/Catalogue
Lesure, François, ed. Catalogue de la musique imprimée avant 1800 conservée dans les bibliotheques publiques de Paris. Paris: Bibliothèque Nationale, 1981.
Marx, Hans Joachim. Die Überlieferung der Werke Arcangelo Corellis: Catalogue rasionné. Cologne: Arno Volk Verlag, 1980.
The New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians. Edited by Stanley Sadie. 20 vols. London: Macmillan, 1980.
The New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians, 2nd ed.. Edited by Stanley Sadie. 29 vols. London: Macmillan, 2001..
Priestman, Brian. "Catalogue thématique des oeuvres de Jean-Baptiste, John et Jacques Loeillet," Revue belge de musicologie, 6 ( 1952 ), pp. 219-274.
RISM
Répertoire international des sources musicales, series A/I. Einzeldrucke vor 1801. Edited by Karl-Heinz Schlager. 10 vols. Kassel: Bärenreiter, 1971-1981.
RISM B/II
Répertoire international des sources musicales, series B, volume 2. Recueils imprimées. Edited by François Lesure. Munich: G. Henle, 1964.
Smith
Smith, William Charles. A Bibliography of the Musical Works Published by John Walsh, During the Years 1695-1720. London: The Bibliographical Society, 1948.
Smith/Handel
Smith, William Charles. Handel: A Descriptive Catalogue of the Early Editions. 2nd edition. New York: Barnes & Noble, 1970.
Smith-Humphries
Smith, William Charles, and Charles Humphries. A Bibliography of the Musical Works Published by the Firm of John Walsh During the Years 1721-1766. London: The Bibliographical Society, 1968.
Terry, Charles Sanford. John Christian Bach. 2nd edition. London: Oxford University Press, 1967.
Vairasse, Denis. Histoire des Sevarambes. Nouvelle édition. Amsterdam: Estienne Roger, 1716. Vol. 2, pp. 291-348: "Catalogue d'un asortiment general de musique, qui se vend à Amsterdam par Estienne Roger".
Wotquenne, Alfred. Catalogue thématique des œuvres de Chr. W. v. Gluck. Leipzig: Breitkopf & Härtel, 1904.
Z. [Purcell]
Zimmerman, Franklin B. Henry Purcell, 1659-1695: An Analytical Catalogue of His Music. New York: St. Martin's Press, 1963.
Z. [Pugnani]
Zschinsky-Troxler, Elisabeth. Gaetano Pugnani, 1731-1798: ein Beitrag zur Stilerfassung italienischer Vorklassik. Berlin: Atlantis, 1939.
Item Listing
- Six QUARTETTO'S for Two Violins, a Tenor, and Violoncello Obligato With a Thorough Bass for the HARPSICHORD, Composed by C. F. ABEL. Opera 15th. Price 1s0.d6. LONDON, Printed by William Napier, No. 474 Strand., ca. 1780; A104; Four parts, quarto, 251x180 (271x201): VIOLINO PRIMO: Title, verso blank. Blank, [1]. Music, pp. 2-16. VIOLINO SECONDO: Title, verso blank. Blank, [1]. Music, pp. 2-13. Blank, [14]. VIOLA: Title, verso blank. Blank, [1]. Music, pp. 2-13. Blank, [14]. VIOLONCELLO: Title, verso blank. Blank, [1]. Music, pp. 2-13. Blank, [14].
  Contents
  QUARTETTO I E
  Allo. ma non troppo C
  Andante con Espressione 2/4
  Tempo di Minuetto 3/4
  QUARTETTO II C
  Allegretto C
  Andante 2/4
  Allegro non tropo 2/4
  QUARTETTO III E♭
  Allegro ma non troppo C
  Adagio ma non troppo 3/8
  Allegretto 2/4
  QUARTETTO IV G
  Allegro C
  Vivace 3/8
  QUARTETTO V F
  Moderato C
  Andante non troppo Adgo. 3/4
  Un Poco Vivace 3/4
  QUARTETTO VI A
  Cantabile 3/4
  Allegro ma non troppo 3/8
  Index Terms
  Quartets, strings, op. 15; Abel, Karl Friedrich, 1723-1787; Napier, William, 1740?-1812; London (England); Minuet; A; C; E; E♭; F; G; 2/4; 3/4; 3/8; Adagio ma non troppo; Allegretto; Allegro; Allegro ma non troppo; Allegro non troppo; Andante; Andante con espressione; Andante non troppo adagio; Cantabile; Moderato; Tempo di minuetto; Un poco vivace; Vivace
  Date source(s)
  BUCEM
  - VIOLINO PRIMO
  - VIOLINO SECONDO
  - VIOLA
  - VIOLONCELLO
- Six SONATAS for a Violin, a Violoncello, & Base with a Thorough Base for the HARPSICHORD Composed by C. F. ABEL, Opera IX. LONDON, Pr. 10/6 Printed for the Author & Sold at his House No. 201, Oxford Street, Sold also by R. Bremner in the Strand., ca. 1770; A126; Three parts, quarto, 269x193 (280x205): VIOLINO: Title, verso blank. Blank, [1]. Music, pp. 2-9. Blank, [10]. VIOLONCELLO: Same as Violino. BASSO: Same as Violino.
  SONATA I A
  SONATA II C
  SONATA III G
  Un poco Vivace 3/4
  SONATA IV B♭
  SONATA V D
  Allegro Moderato C
  Minuet 3/4
  SONATA VI F
  Sonatas, violin, violoncello, bass, op. 9; Abel, Karl Friedrich, 1723-1787; Bremner, Robert, d. 1789; London (England); Minuet; A; B♭; C; D; F; G; 3/4; 3/8; Allegretto; Allegro; Allegro moderato; Minuet; Moderato; Tempo di minuetto; Un poco vivace; Vivace
  Advertised in Bremner's 1772 publication of the composer's op. 10 (Knape, p. 139).
  Two copies are in the collection.
  - VIOLINO
  - VIOLONCELLO
  - BASSO
- Six SONATAS FOR Two Violins, or a German Flute and Violin, with a Thorough Bass for the HARPSICHORD, Dedicated To the Right Honourable The EARL of ASCHBURNHAM &c. Composed by Charles Frederick Abel. OPERA III LONDON Printed for the Author and sold at his Lodgings, at the Dial in Greek Street St. Ann's Soho., ca. 1765; A109; Three parts, folio, 254x178 (265x188): VIOLINO PRIMO: Title, verso blank. Blank, [1]. Music, pp. 2-13. Blank, [14]. VIOLINO SECONDO: Title, verso blank. Blank, [1]. Music, pp. 2-11. Blank, [12]. At bottom right of p. 11: "Engrav'd by Rd. Alderman". BASSO: Title, verso blank. Music, pp. 1-11. Blank, [12].
  SONATA I G
  Vivace C
  Adagio ma non troppo 3/4
  Minuetto 3/8
  Minuetto 3/4
  SONATA III B♭
  Menuetto 3/4
  SONATA IV D
  Andantino 2/4
  Menuetto 3/4 ["4" omitted in VIOLINO PRIMO]
  SONATA V A
  Allegro di Molto C
  Cantabile 3/8
  Menuetto 3/8
  SONATA VI E♭
  Un poco Adagio C
  Trio sonatas, op. 3; Abel, Karl Friedrich, 1723-1787; London (England); Minuet; A; B♭; C; D; E♭; G; 2/4; 3/4; 3/8; Adagio ma non troppo; Allegro; Allegro di molto; Andante; Andantino; Cantabile; Menuetto; Minuetto; Moderato; Un poco adagio; Vivace
  - VIOLINO PRIMO
  - VIOLINO SECONDO
  - BASSO
- SIX SONATAS two for a Violin, Tenor and Violoncello two for Two Violins and a Thorough Bass. two for One Flute a Violin & Thorough Bass Composed by GIUSEPPE AGUS Opera Sesta. NB: At the end of the Book the 1st. and 2d. Trios are Transposed & adapted for the Violin instead of the Tenor, the 1st. & 2d. Trio's are also adapted for the Harpsichord instead of the VIOLONCELLO. LONDON Printed and Sold by WELCKER No. 9 Hay Market opposite ye Opera House. Where may be had Just Publish'd. 6 Quartetts for 2 Violins a Tenor and Bass by Sigr. Paisaible 10=6. 6 Sonatas for the Piano Forte or Harpsd. with Accompts. by Antonio Kammell. 10=6 &c. &c. &c., ca. 1775; A459; Three parts, quarto, 263x198 (272x201): VIOLINO PRIMO: Title, verso blank. Blank, [1]. Music, pp. 2-13. Blank, [14]. VIOLA OBLIGATO: Title, verso blank. Blank, [1]. Music, pp. 2-17. From p. 6 onward, the heading is "VIOLINO SECONDO", with the works presented in the order III, IV, V, VI, I, and II. VIOLONCELLO OBLIGATO: Title, verso blank. Blank, [1]. Music, pp. 2-22. Pages 14-22 are Trios I and II arranged for harpsichord, with figured bass.
  TRIO I C
  All: moderato C
  Andante C
  TRIO II D
  Allegro C|
  Andante C|
  All: mod: 2/4
  TRIO III G
  Andante 3/4
  Allegro non tanto 2/4
  TRIO IV A
  Larghetto 3/4
  Allo. non tanto 6/8
  TRIO V D
  TRIO VI A
  Trio sonatas, op. 6; Agus, Giuseppe; Welcker, John; Welcker, John; Welcker, John; London (England); Minuet; A; C; D; G; 2/4; 3/4; 6/8; C|; Allegro moderato; Allegro; Allegro non tanto; Andante; Larghetto; Minuet; Moderato; Tempo di minuetto
  - VIOLINO PRIMO
  - VIOLA OBLIGATO
  - VIOLONCELLO OBLIGATO
- XII SUONATE a Tre Duoi Violini e Violone Col Basso per L'Organo DEDICATE Al Molto Reverendo e Molto illustre Signore il Signor DECANO E CAPITOLO CRANENBURGHENSE Da PIETRO ALBERTI Organista del Capitolo Cranenburghense OPERA PRIMA A Amsterdam Chez ESTIENNE ROGER Marchand Libraire, 1703; A681; Four parts, folio, 234x182 (302 x ? [right edge of each title-page has been trimmed]): Violino Primo: Title, verso blank. Letter of dedication, verso blank, [i-ii]. Music, pp. 1-20. Violino Secondo: Title, verso blank. Music, pp. 1-19. Blank, [20]. Violoncello: Title, verso blank. Music, pp. 1-20. Organo: Title, verso blank. Music, pp. 1-18. All four title-pages signed: "Alberti". "1706" added in MS on title-page of Violino Primo between "OPERA PRIMA" and "A Amsterdam".
  Sonata I d
  Grave e Tremolo C
  Allegro 3/4
  Adagio C
  Vivace 3/4
  Allegro 12/8
  Sonata II D
  Grave C
  Adagio e Tremolo C
  Sonata III g
  Adagio 3/2
  Allegro 6/8
  Sonata IV C
  Presto 12/8
  Sonata V a
  Adagio 3/4
  Sonata VI F
  Allegro 3/8
  Sonata VII c
  Sonata VIII G
  Sonata IX e
  Sonata X E♭
  Sonata XI b
  Allegro 6/4
  Presto C
  Sonata XII B♭
  Trio sonatas, op. 1; Alberti, Pietro; Roger, Estienne, 1665-1722; Amsterdam (Netherlands); B♭; C; D; E♭; F; G; A; B; E; 12/8; 3/2; 3/4; 3/8; 6/4; 6/8; Adagio; Adagio e tremolo; Allegro; Grave; Grave e tremolo; Presto; Vivace
  Announced in
  The Post Man
  , April 29 and May 27, 1703.
  Lesure/Bibliographie, p. 43
  - Violino Primo
  - Violino Secondo
  - Violoncello
  - Organo
- SIX SONATAS or NOTTURNAS, for Two VIOLINS and BASS. Composed BY Sigr Giuseppe Albertini. LONDON: Printed for A: HUMMEL at his Musick Shop facing Nasau Street in King Street St. Anns Soho, where may had Just publishd Six Favourite Overtures for Violins, Frenchhorns &c. Compos'd by Sigr. Galuppi, Sigr. St. Martini, and Sigr. Jomelli. Likewise great choice of new Musick both English and Foreign., ca. 1770? Publisher active between 1760 and 1770 (Humphries-Smith, p. 189); the collection of overtures advertised on the title-page appeared ca. 1770; A685; Three parts, folio, 241x168 (266x186): VIOLINO PRIMO: Title, verso blank. Blank, [1]. Music, pp. 2-13. Blank, [14]. VIOLINO SECONDO: Title, verso blank. Blank, [1]. Music, pp. 2-11. Blank, [12]. BASSO: Title, verso blank. Music, pp. 1-6. Blank, [7].
  SONATA I C
  Larghetto C|
  SONATA II B♭
  Largo C|
  SONATA III A
  SONATA IV E♭
  Allegro 2/4
  SONATA VI E
  Largo 2/4
  Trio sonatas; Albertini, Giuseppe; Hummell, A.; London (England); Minuet; A; B♭; C; E; E♭; 2/4; 3/4; C|; Allegro; Andante; Andantino; Larghetto; Largo; Menuetto; Minuetto
  - VIOLINO PRIMO
  - VIOLINO SECONDO
  - BASSO
- XII SUONATE à Tre Due Violini e Violoncello Col Basso per l'Organo Dal Signor HENRICI ALBICASTERO D.B.W. Cavaliero Opera Quarta A Amsterdam Chez ESTIENNE ROGER Marchand libraire, 1702; A692; Four parts, folio, 217x157 (286x182): Violino Primo: Title, verso blank. Music, pp. 1-15. Blank, [16]. Two blanks, [17-18]. Violino Secondo: Same as Violino Primo. Violoncello: Title, verso blank. Music, pp. 1-13. Blank, [14]. Two blanks, [15-16]. Organo: Title, verso blank. Music, pp. 1-16. Two blanks, [17-18]. All four title-pages signed: "Albicastero". "1715" added in MS on title-page of Violino Primo between "Opera Quarta" and "A Amsterdam". "1700" added in MS on title-page of Violoncello after "Opera Quarta".
  Sonata I D
  Grave 3/2
  Prestissimo 2/4
  Sonata II g
  Poco Presto C
  Sonata III B♭
  Spiritoso C
  Sonata IV A
  Grave 3/4
  Sonata V F
  Sonata VI a
  Affectuoso 3/4
  Sonata VIII b
  Sonata IX d
  Sonata X G
  Presto à 3 C
  Sonata XI C
  Sonata XII E
  Affectuoso C
  Trio sonatas, op. 4; Albicastro, Henricus; Roger, Estienne, 1665-1722; Amsterdam (Netherlands); A; B♭; C; D; E; F; G; B; 2/4; 3/2; 3/4; 3/8; 6/8; Adagio; Affectuoso; Allegro; Andante; Grave; Poco presto; Prestissimo; Presto; Presto à 3; Spiritoso
  Announced in Vairasse (Lesure/Bibliographie, p. 42).
  - Violino Primo
  - Violino Secondo
  - Violoncello
  - Organo